Ciaran Carson papers, circa 1970-2010
Emory University
- Writings by Carson, circa 1970-2009, Series 2; Boxes 8-28, 48-59; OP1-5
  - Prose, 1985-2009, Subseries 2.4; Boxes 21-28, 57-59; OP 3-5
    - "Entering the Realms of Make-Believe," TS review of The Something in Particular by John Hughes and A Story of Candles by Frank Ormsby (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - "How to Remember," TS review of The Ulster Renaissance: Poetry in Belfast 1962-1972, for Field Day Review by Heather Clark, 3 December 2006 (Box 59, Folder 22)
    - "Like a Cicada in Someone's Hand," TS review of No, I'm Not Afraid by Irina Ratushinskaya (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - "The Man who goes to Hell," TS review of Dante: The Poet, the Political Thinker, The Man by Barbara Reynolds, June 2006 [fragment] (Box 59, Folder 23)
    - "Many Mansions," TS review of Jorie Graham's Swarm and Kit Wright's Hoping It Might Be So, with ALS from CC, 15 January 2001, includes proof of review with variant title: "A Lot of Buzzing Around the Bush; and also a Poet to Enjoy" [See also Subseries 4.1: Poetry London, spring 2000] (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - "Mirror Writing," TS review of Richard Murphy's The Kick (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - "Realms of Gold," TS review of Venice: A Collection of the Poetry of Place, ed. by Hetty Meryric Hughes, circa 2006 (Box 59, Folder 24)
    - Untitled, TS review of An Duanaire by Seán O'Tuama and Thomas Kinsella (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, TS review of Katerina Brae by Christopher Reid (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Untitled, TS review of Mary Mary's Last Dance, September 2002 (Box 59, Folder 25)
    - Untitled, MS and TS review of Narrative Singing in Ireland by Hugh Shields (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Untitled, TS review of The New Oxford Book of Irish Verse ed. by Thomas Kinsella (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Untitled, TS review of O Bruadair translated by Michael Hartnett (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Untitled, TS review of Sam Henry's Songs of the People ed. by Gale Huntington (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Untitled, TS review of Sweeney Astray by Seamus Heaney (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Untitled, TS review of The Truth Commissioner by David Park, circa March 2008 (Box 59, Folder 26)
    - Untitled, TS review of An tAthair Pádraug Ó Duinnin -- Bleachtaire and Oiche Bhealtaine by Biddy Jenkinson, circa 2008 (Box 59, Folder 27)
  - Scripts, 1985-2005, Subseries 2.5; Boxes 28, 59
    This subseries contains typescripts of scripts for television and radio written by Carson from 1985-2005, including a proposal for a stage adaptation of Belfast Confetti.
    - Belfast Confetti, proposal for 1994 stage adaptation [includes project correspondence: ALS from Dave O'Meara to Carson, ALS from Carson to O'Meara, and ALS from Carson to Dillon Johnston] (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - "Chief O'Neill's Favourites," TS BBC radio script (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - "Cuchullain in the Land of Shadows," TS February 1986 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - "The Destruction of Dun Rig," TS June 1985 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - "Following the Stream," TS for BBC film Tí Chulainn, 11 September 1998 (Box 59, Folder 28)
    - "Imram Táin," TS [in Irish and English] (Box 59, Folder 29)
    - "Radio On, Radio Off," piece for Radio Ulster, 11 July 2005 (Box 59, Folder 30)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: The Gift of Ink / Michael J. Murphy" TS Spring 1988 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: Trams," TS Autumn 1988 (Box 28, Folder 19)
  - Interviews, 1989-2009, Subseries 2.6; Box 28, 59
    This subseries contains transcripts of interviews of Carson from 1989-2009.
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Rand Brandes, Madden's Bar, Belfast, 8 August 1989 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Frank Ormsby," for Linen Hall Review, April 1991 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Niall McGrath, 1994 with ALS from Niall McGrath, 1 July 1994 (Box 28, Folder 22)
    - Interview of Carson, TS by Johannah Raney, 28 November 1995, with TLS from Raney 11 December 1995 (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Thomas Rain Crowe for Asheville Poetry Review, 4 June 1996 with ALS from TRC, 22 June 1996 [See also Subseries 4.2: "The Irony of Northern Ireland and the War With Words" in The Blooomsbury Review] (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Francesca Bovone, with TLS 16 June 1999 [interview completed 1 September 1997] (Box 28, Folder 25)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS ["Inventing Carson"] by David Laskowski, August 1999 (Box 28, Folder 26)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by John Brown, circa 2000 (Box 28, Folder 27)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Jacek Gutorow, circa summer 2000, with ALS from The British Council in Poland, 17 November 2000 (Box 28, Folder 28)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Angel Gurria, June 2002 (Box 28, Folder 29)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by unknown interviewer, for "Derry News," 12 March 2004 (Box 59, Folder 31)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Jenny Malmqvist, circa 2007 (Box 59, Folder 32)
    - Interview of Ciaran Carson, TS by Elmer Kennedy-Andrews, "For all I know: Ciaran Carson in conversation with Elmer Kennedy-Andrews," for Four Courts Press book of essays on Carson, circa 2009 (Box 59, Folder 33)
- Writings by others, 1977-2007, Series 3; Boxes 29-31, 60
  This series contains writings by other authors sent to Carson including writings about Carson and other general works from 1977-2007. Writings include poetry, prose fiction, essays, and reviews and critical readings of Carson's work. Poetry is by various contemporary Irish and American poets and translators, including Tess Gallagher, Eavan Boland, Paul Muldoon, Michael Longley, John Montague, Liam O'Muirthile, and Theo Dorgan. The poetry section also includes some translations of Carson's poems. Prose fiction and drama is predominately by Tess Gallagher. Writings about Carson include reviews, conference papers, and essays by students, journalists, and academics working on Carson's writing. Other writings within this series are essays and dissertations on traditional music, musical scores, essays on history and geography, as well as works of biography or autobiography.
  Organized into four subseries: (3.1) Poetry by others, (3.2) Prose fiction and drama by others, (3.3) Writings about Carson, (3.4) Other writings.
  - Poetry by others, 1977-2007, Subseries 3.1; Boxes 29-30, 60
    This subseries contains poetry by others received by Carson from 1977-2007. Much of the collected poetry is related to a special edition of The Back Door, focusing on younger Irish poets. Poets' typescripts gathered for this project are indicated with: [The Back Door]. Correspondence related to this project is in Series 7: Subject files. Carson amassed a number of contributions, but the project never reached fruition. Carson has also received various drafts of poetry from friends and colleagues including Tess Gallagher, Michael Longley, Liam O'Muirthile, and Paul Muldoon. This series also includes translations of Carson's poems by others.
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Boland, Eavan: TS for The Back Door include: "The Gorgon Child," "In His own Image," "In Her Own Image," "Woman in Kitchen," "The Muse Mother," "Monotony,"with TLS from Boland, 22 July 1977 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Comiskey, John: TS of The Well, a stage production of traditional music and published poetry by various writers including: Ciaran Carson ["Céilí"], George Mackay Brown, Norman MacCaig, Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill, Michael Hartnett, Thomas Kinsella, Richard Murphy, Seán Dunne, Paul Durcan, Carol Ann Duffy, among others; arranged for the Dublin Theatre Festival 2000 [See also Subseries 2.4: "The Well"] (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Dale, Peter Nicholas: TS, Translations of Giuseppe Gioachimo Belli's sonnets, with correspondence between Carson and Dale, 6 April 2005 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Dorgan, Theo: TS, "General de Gaulle's Alexandrine Rag-Time," [circa 1998] (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Foley, Michael: TS for The Back Door include: "The Ghost of James Joyce," "The Wife's Complaint," "The Husband's Message," "Pierrot's Melancholy" [after Laforgue], "Sundays," "Young Couple" [after Rimbaud], "To Mount Etna" [after Corbie?e], with ALS from Foley, 9 September 1977 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS, "Invaded by Souls," "The Kiss in Her Bath," "The Kiss Takes Confession," "The Kiss Considers Capital Punishment As She Motors Toward Seattle," "The Kiss Gets a New Bonnet," "Shadow Talk," "Urgent Story," with TLS from Gallagher, 12 June 1993 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS for "Choices" [autumn 1999] (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Gillis, Alan: TS, Hawks and Doves, with correspondence between Carson and Gillis, 4 September 2006 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Gillis, Alan: TS with corrections, Somebody, Somewhere, with correspondence between Carson and Gillis, 2 July 2004 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Heaney, Seamus: "Servant Boy," "The Last Mummer," "Gifts of Rain," "The Tollund Man," "Westering;" [See Series 5: Belfast Group Worksheets] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Hinds, Michael, TS Le Jeu Avant Tout (1999) [See also Series 1: Correspondence from Hinds, 10 February 1999] (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Hughes, John: TS, poems (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Hughes, John: TS, poems with ALS from Hughes, All Saints Day, 1995 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Hughes, John: TS, poems with correspondence between Hughes and Carson, November 2001 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Johnstone, Robert: TS for The Back Door include: "Divorce," "There Existed Another Ending to the Story of O," "Autobiography," "Working with Cauliflowers,"with ALS from Johnstone, 6 September 1977 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Johnstone, Robert: TS, "'Murdering Democracy' Talking Blues," "Supergrass," with ALS from Johnstone, 4 September 1986 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Jordan, June: TS, faxed copy of "Love Song About Choosing Your Booze," 1993 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Lindsey, Jim: TS, "Unheard Voices of the Rich," translation of Roberto Sosa (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Lindsey, Jim: TS, poem with verse letter from Lindsey, 13 November 1978 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Longley, Michael: "Altera Cithera," "Three Posthumous Pieces," "The Island," "Casualty," "Badger," "Hedgehog," "Kingfisher," "Robin," "The Adulterer;" [See Series 5: Belfast Group Worksheets] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Longley, Michael: TS for The Back Door include: "Epitaph" [in memoriam Patrick Kavanah], "Propaganda," "The End of the War," "Home Ground," "Brothers," "Self-Heal," "Botany," "New Born" (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Longley, Michael: TS, "Font" [for Manus Carson], with Longley's autograph: "Blessings / Uncle Mickey / August 89" (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Martin, Carl: TS, poems (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Marshall, Douglas: TS for The Back Door include: Upstairs Neighbours, "Welcome," with ALS from Marshall, August 1977 (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - McCabe, Cathal: TS, translations of Polish poems, with correspondence from McCabe, 11 October 2004 (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - McCauley, Amy: TS, poem, no date (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - McEwen, R.F.: TS, "Small Favors," no date (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - McMahon, Trevor: "Moth," "Worm," "The Planter Speaks," "Old Man," "To Those Involved in Rigid Disciplines," "Rat Song," "The Fool's Soliloquy," "Poem as Mammoth;" [See Series 5: Belfast Group Worksheets] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Meehan, Paula: "Home," TS, with ALS 19 September 1993 (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Montague, John: TS for The Back Door include: "The Blue Room," "Waiting," "Working Dream," "The Point," "Talisman," with note from Montague (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Muldoon, Paul: "Blowing Eggs," "The Radio Horse," "The Field Hospital," "On a Dog of Unlike Eyes," "The Lost Tribe," "The Upriver Incident," "Party Piece;" [See Series 5: Belfast Group Worksheets] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Muldoon, Paul: TS for The Back Door include: "Lull," "Truce," "Cuba," "The Weepies" (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Muldoon, Paul: TS, The Annals of Chile, with fax from Carson, 8 February 1994 (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Muldoon, Paul: corrected proofs, The Prince of the Quotidian, with ALS from Peter Fallon, 31 March 1994 (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Ni Dhomhnaill, Nuala [?], "Ni de chuid an tsaoil seo," TS (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Ni Uallachain, Padraigin: TS, A Stor's A Stoirin [part 1], with introduction by Carson [1994] (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Ni Uallachain, Padraigin: TS A Stor's A Stoirin [part 2], [1994] (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - O'Kelly, Patrick: TS, "The Litany for Doneraile," no date (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - O'Muirthile, Liam: TS "Dán I gCuimhne Ar Mheáig Howley," "An Luascán," "Domhnach Cásca," [31 May 1995] (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - O'Muirthile, Liam: TS "Galar an ghrá," [July 1999] (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Paulin, Tom: TS for The Back Door include: "Trotsky in Finland," "The Eye's Parish," "Anastasia McLaughlin," "At Lockjaw Hall," "Still Century," "Going in the Rain," with ALS from Paulin, 6 September 1977 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Peskett, William: TS for The Back Door include: "New Year in an Empty Church," "Copy," "Camping on Dunwhich Cliff," with TLS from Peskett, 25 July 1977 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Radicchi, Alessandra: TS, translations of Edoardo Zuccato's poems, with correspondence from Zuccato, 13 January 1997 (Box 60, Folder 8)
    - Sasaki, Mikiro: TS, poem, "A Messenger of the Wind," (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Scott, M.E.: TS, "Two for Joy?" 19 October 2007 (Box 60, Folder 9)
    - Sewell, Frankie: TS, poems with commentary by Carson; plus TLS by Carson to Sewell, 13 January 1994 and ALS from Sewell, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Takahashi, Mutsuo: TS, poems, "That Morning," "I-Myth (Private Myth)" (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Verner, Scott: TS, "Blue Grass," [after: "Calvin Klein's Obsession"] (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Walsh, Thomas: TS, poems with TLS from Walsh, 7 February 1994 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Walsh, Thomas: TS, poems, with ALS from Walsh, 18 May 1994 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Waterfield, John: TS, "The Fourth Elegy," translation of Rainer Maria Rilke, 12 November 2003 (Box 60, Folder 10)
    - Assorted students' poetry (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified authors: TS, poems (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified authors: TS, poems, Poetry London Competition, 2002 (Box 60, Folder 11)
    - Translations of Carson
    - Bertoni, Roberto: TS, Italian translations of selections from The New Estate to Opera Et Cetera, [December 1997] (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Carson notes on French translations of Carson's Poems, with correspondence, 13 November 2003 (Box 60, Folder 12)
    - Farina, Raymond: TS, French translations of "Catmint Tea," "The Millfield Foundry Belfast," "One Exchange Place," "Spot the Wallop," "Tru-Fit Exhausts;" with ALS from Farina, 30 June 2001 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - "Last Night's Fun," translated into Italian by Davide Benini (Box 60, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified author: TS, Swedish translations of Breaking News, no date (Box 60, Folder 14)
    - Questions and replies concerning Russian translations of Carson's poems, 20 September 2002 (Box 60, Folder 15)
    - Schneider, Jurgen: TS, German translations of Carson's poems (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Tochigi, Nobuaki, translation of "Antipodes" (from Fishing for Amber) [See Subseries 4.2: Writing About Carson, "Introduction to the Poetry of Ciaran Carson"] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Zuccato, Edoardo: TS, Italian translations of Carson's poems, with TLS, 11 December 1996 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Zuccato, Edoardo, translation of "Belfast Confetti," [See Subseries 4.2: Writing About Carson, "Poesia Inglese: La Generazione Degli Anni Settanta," by Edoardo Zuccato] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Zuccato, Edoardo, "Collecting Stamps," [See Subseries 4.2: Writing about Carson, "Poesia Inglese: La Generazione Degli Anni Settanta," by Edoardo Zuccato] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Zuccato, Edoardo, "The Irish for No," [See Subseries 4.2, Writing about Carson: "Poesia Inglese: La Generazione Degli Anni Settanta," by Edoardo Zuccato] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Prose fiction and drama by others, 1985-2005, Subseries 3.2; Boxes 30, 60
    This subseries contains prose fiction and drama by others received by Carson from 1985-2005. Much of this subseries is comprised of works by Tess Gallagher. This series also includes translations of Carson's prose works by others.
    - Durcan, Paul: TS, "The Poet as Chronicler of Modernity: Cronin's Cantos," Ireland Professor of Poetry Inaugural Lecture, 3 March 2005 (Box 60, Folder 16)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS of story, "Angel Foot: A Double Portrait," 2 July 1997 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS of story "Bad Company" [See also Subseries 3.2: "The Leper" by Tess Gallagher] (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Gallagher, Tess: galley of "The Leper," with TLS from Gallagher 13 June 1985 [See also Subseries 4.3: "Again" by Tess Gallagher] (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS of story, "The Poetry Baron," circa 1995-1996 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS of story, Surrounded by Weasels: Stories from the West of Ireland, with correspondence, 10 March 2000 [1 of 2] (Box 60, Folder 17)
    - Gallagher, Tess: TS of story, Surrounded by Weasels: Stories from the West of Ireland, 10 March 2000 [2 of 2] (Box 60, Folder 18)
    - Mac Intyre, Tom: TS of play, Sheep's Milk on the Boil, with introduction by Carson: "The Night Before, the Morning After," 3 March 1994 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - MacLaverty, Bernard: "The Deep End;" [See Series 5: Belfast Group Worksheets] (Box -, Folder -)
    - McKay, Susan: TS, "Bear in Mind These Dead," The Irish Times, no date (Box 60, Folder 19)
    - Morrow, John: TS of story, "Travels with the Sound Man" (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Muldoon, Paul: TS of libretto, Six Honest Serving Men (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - Translations of Carson
    - Thé au Trèste, TS of translation of Carson's Shamrock Tea, no date (Box 60, Folder 20)
  - Writings about Carson, 1989-2006, Subseries 3.3; Boxes 31, 60
    This subseries contains writings about Carson from 1989-2006. Writings include reviews, conference papers, and essays by students, journalists, and academics working on Carson's writing.
    - Batten, Guinn: TS "Belfast Crack: Ciaran Carson's Parturient Partition," TS, [1992] (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Batten, Guinn: TS "Professional Mourning and Poetic Melancholy" [from The Orphaned Imagination, 1998], TS (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Brandes, Rand: "Ciaran Carson's Belfast Confetti: Politics and Beyond," TS with ALS from Brandes, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Brandes, Rand: "Ciaran Carson's The Irish for No," TS with TLS from Brandes, 16 June 1989 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Brandes, Rand: "Surreal Solutions: Paul Muldoon and Ciaran Carson," TS with TLS from Brandes, 1 January 1990 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Brandes, Rand: "The Body and History in Seamus Heaney's 'Digging' and Ciaran Carson's 'Bloody Hand,'" TS with TLS from Brandes, 13 April 1992 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Burleigh, David: "'Echoes Trickling in..' - Japan in the Work Irish Writers," TS with TLS from Burleigh, 11 October 1993 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Corcoran, Neil: "One Step Forward, Two Steps Back: Ciaran Carson's The Irish for No," TS (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - De Angelis, Irene: 'The Labyrinth to which I hadn't got the Key': Ciaran Carson's View of Japan, September 2006 (Box 60, Folder 21)
    - Harden, Geoff: "Ciaran Carson," TS, August/September 1997 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Hufstader, Jonathan: Untitled TS essay with TL from Carson, 9 December 1994 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Hughes, Eamonn: "Brain-damaged and dangerous: Belfast in fiction," TS (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Hughes, Eamonn: "'Town of Shadows': Representations of Belfast in Recent Irish Fiction," TS (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Johnston, Dillon: "Irish Poets who are also Women," TS with TLS from Carson, 14 September 1995 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Sarbin, Deborah: "'We are all now dispossessed': Postmodern History in Northern Irish Poetry," TS with TLC from Sarbin, 19 March 1992 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Tochigi, Nobuaki: "Reeling with Words: Music and Intoxication in Ciaran Carson's Alphabetical Sequences" [presented September 1997 at Tokyo IASIL Conference]; TS plus assorted Carson panel handouts from various presenters. (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified author: TS, "Seeking a Common Tongue: Carson, Dante, Belfast," no date (Box 60, Folder 22)
  - Other writings, 1994-1998, Subseries 3.4; Box 31
    This subseries contains other collected writings from 1994-1998. Writings include essays and dissertations on traditional music, musical scores, essays on history and geography, as well as works of biography and autobiography.
    - Brennan-Corcoran, Helen: "Dancing on a Plate: the Sean-Nós Dance Tradition of Conamara," TS dissertation [1994] (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Donleavy, (?): TS copy of scores and commentary on traditional Irish music scores (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Foy, Barry: The Field Guide to the Irish Music Session, TS with TSL from Foy, 14 February 1998 (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Gallagher, Tess: "Preface" [incomplete] of Soul Barnacles, TS (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Gallagher, Tess: "Introduction" for All of Us: The Collected Poems of Raymond Carver, TS with TLS from Gallagher, 22 April 1996 (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Keery, Sam: "Irishness," TS (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Leach, Roger: "Joe Cooley," TS with ALS from Charlie Piggion(?), 24 September 1998 (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Longley, Michael: TS list of selected twentieth-century Irish poems (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - Newon, George: "Aisling Gheal," MS of musical score written "for Ciaran Carson and Deidre; Shannon" (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Robinson, Tim: "Four Threads," TS with note by Carson on relevance to The Star Factory (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Robinson, Tim: "Secret Connemara," TS of paper given at CAIS Toronto, 1994 (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified: "Irish Traditional Music: the Myth of its Popularity," TTS with TLS (Box 31, Folder 27)
- Printed material, 1975-2008, Series 4; Boxes 32 - 40, 61-62; OP 6 - 26
  This series contains printed material collected by Carson from 1976-2002. Materials in this series include items by and about Carson, as well as more general, collected material. Printed material by Carson includes various poems, essays, and reviews by Carson, as well as a number of published translations of his work. Of particular interest is an extensive run of essays by Carson from the mid-1980s published in the Belfast Review. Printed material about Carson includes essays and articles about Carson, as well as reviews of his writings. This series also contains promotional material created by Carson's publishers; correspondence, programs, and flyers from Carson's numerous readings and lectures; essays by and about Carson's friends; various journals sent with solicitations for contributions of poetry; several Irish studies journals to which Carson has contributed; photocopies of songs; occasional broadsides; and assorted printed interviews and reviews. One peculiar item is Carson's personal rhyming dictionary used for works up to and including his 2002 translation of Dante's Inferno.
  Organized into three subseries: (4.1) Printed material by Ciaran Carson, (4.2) Printed material about Ciaran Carson, and (4.3) Other printed material.
  - Printed material by Carson, 1975-2007, Subseries 4.1; Box 32 - Box 34, 61; OP6 - 12
    - "Against Oblivion" [review of C.K. Williams], no date (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - "Alibi," [poem] in Poems of the Decade: An Anthology of the Forward Books of Poetry 1992-2001 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - "Ambition," corrected proofs with 2 accompanying TLS from Alice Quinn (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - "Apparat," [poem] in The Irish Times, 17 July 1993 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - "Aranmore Ireland 1. Erratics" in The Irish Press, undated (Box OP6, Folder -)